Guide to the Marjorie Echols Local Artists Collection MS 035
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Marjorie Echols Local Artists Collection
1925-2000
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Echols, Marjorie
MS 035
10 Linear Feet 52 prints, pencil drawings, paintings, photographs, silk screen prints and watercolors
The collection includes works of art collected by Marjorie Echols '81. The art is in various mediums and was created by artists from the Danbury area.
Provenance
Donated by Marjorie Echols in early 2007
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Marjorie Echols received a Bachelor of Arts in Art from WestConn in 1981. Before earning that degree, Echols took electives in several different areas with the ultimate intent of receiving a B.S.N. degree. However, the art electives proved to be of such interest, that she ended up being part of the first graphic design graduating class at WestConn.
After graduating, Echols went on to a career working with contemporary Danbury artists at the Downtown Gallery which rented art to area businesses and individuals and she owned The Art Store in Danbury which offered art classes, a frame shop, gallery and art supplies. Echols served on the board of the Richter Association for the Arts, was a founder of Still River Artists, and is a signature member of the National Acrylic Painters Association (works exhibited through the National Acrylic Painters Association are archived in the Tate Museum in London).
In addition, she combined her nursing background with her love of art as a certified psychiatric nurse. In this role she worked with Vietnam veterans at the West Haven Veterans Administration Hospital and the National Center for Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder. She's also used art therapy to work with blind, deaf and physically impaired individuals
Echols has maintained close ties to WestConn and its art department and her collecting has been firmly rooted in the arts community of Danbury.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is made up of pieces by local artists, among them: Jack Barrows, Doron Ben-Ami, Tish Bronson, Robert Capilaro, Lynn Currie, William Geisse, Joy Ginsberg, Andrei Houdiakoff, Lizbeth Clifton Hunter, Dot Hurd, Jake Krapowicz, Karl Kravatz, Dar Luckinbil, Harold Nicholson, Richard Procopio, Roy Riadabok, Dennis Stuart, Kim Tester and Ida Mae Wanzer.
Arrangement
Items are arranged by type
The items are grouped into 1 series.
Missing Title
Inventory
Danbury (Conn.); Photographs.; Drawings.; Watercolors (paintings).; Oil paintings.; Wanzer, Ida Mae.; Bronson, Tish.; Ben Ami, Doron.; Currie, Lynn.; Capllaro, Robert.; Echols, Marjorie; Barrows, Jack.; Houdiakoff, Andrei 1895-1985; Hunter, Elizabeth Clifton (Lizbeth C. Hunter); Hurd, Dot.; Geisse, William.; Ginsberg, Joy.; Procopio, Richard.; Ridebock, Ray.; Stuart, Dennis.; Tester, Kim.; Krapowicz, Jake.; Kravatz, Karl.; Luckenbill, Darr; Nicholson, Harold O., III
- Inventory
  - P.T. Barnum Square, Bethel, Jack Barrows, undated (Folder OS Folder 4, Item 1)
    General note
    Print
  - Vietnam Veterans Memorial, Danbury, Jack Barrows, undated (Folder OS Folder 4, Item 2)
  - Bethel Train Station, Jack Barrows, undated (Folder OS Folder 4, Item 3)
  - Shirtless Man With Boot, Doron Ben Ami, 1979 (Folder OS Folder 2, Item 5)
    Pencil Drawing
  - Blinds, Tish Bronson, 1982 (Folder OS Folder 9, Item 4)
    Silk Screen Print
  - Orange, floral print ("artist proof"), Tish Bronson, undated (Folder OS Folder 9, Item 3)
  - Day Lilies, Tish Bronson, undated (Folder OS Folder 9, Item 1)
    Silk screen print purple ink.
  - Blue, Tish Bronson, undated (Folder OS Folder 9, Item 2)
    Silk screen print
  - Red Flower on Green Background, Robert Capellaro, undated (Folder OS Folder 6, Item 1)
    Photograph
  - "Peony"; Pink Flower, Robert Capellaro, undated (Folder OS Folder 6, Item 2)
  - [Seated Contemplative Woman Print], Lynn Currie, undated (Item 3)
    Print 2/4. Print of charcoal drawing.
  - Stone building, by Marjorie Echols, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    5 x 7" glass framed Photograph
  - Sketch for Prince Hall (Tracing of African American man, colonial period), William Geisse, 1991 (Folder OS Folder 2, Item 1)
  - [Middle Eastern Woman Seated], Joy Ginsberg, undated (Folder OS Folder 6, Item 3)
  - [Abstract multiple medium print on fabric] - Andrei Houdiakoff, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Print mounted on masonite. Approximately, 8x10"
  - [Woman Seated], Andrei Houdiakoff, undated (Item 4)
    Oil on canvass
  - [Children's Train], 7 panel painting, Andrei Houdiakoff, 1930s (Folder OS Folder 5, Item 3, Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    Panels originally were all connected.
  - [Crime Scene], figures posed around figure on ground, creator: Andrei Houdiakoff, undated (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 2)
    Pen on paper
  - [Farm Scene], Andrei Houdiakoff, 1920s (Folder OS Folder 7, Item 2)
    Charcoal on paper
  - "Sunday News", Andrei Houdiakoff, 1954 (Item 6)
  - [Barn, Cows and Tree] (1925), Andrei Houdiakoff (Folder OS Folder 7, Item 1)
    Charcoal on paper.
  - [Barn and Tree], Andrei Houdiakoff, undated (Item 11)
  - [Tank and Clown with blue trousers and Soviet flag], Andrei Houdiakoff, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 1)
    Painting
  - [Virgin Mary with Three images of Christ ], Andrei Houdiakoff, undated (Folder OS Folder 7, Item 3)
    Pen and ink on paper
  - [Abstract] small painting, Andrei Houdiakoff, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Painting, oil on canvass
  - [Abstract Orange Triangle, Green Square], Andrei Houdiakoff, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [Knights in Combat], Andrei Houdiakoff, undated (Folder OS Folder 7, Item 4)
  - [City Skyline], Andrei Houdiakoff, undated (Box 1, Folder 7, Item 3)
    Ink on paper, lacquered.
  - [Street Scene] Polperro in Cornwall, England?, Hunter, Elizabeth Clifton (Lizbeth C. Hunter), undated (Folder OS Folder 1)
  - Waterfall, Dot Hurd, undated (Item 5)
    Painting, framed
  - New York Central Diesel Engine, Ittedora, 1987 (Folder OS Folder 2, Item 2-4)
    Prints
  - Beach Scene watercolor by L. R. Kolerzen, 1987 (Folder OS Folder 3, Item 2)
    Watercolor painting
  - [Tree Trunk with Mushrooms], Jake Krapowicz, undated (Folder OS Folder 8, Item 6)
    Watercolor painting; matted
  - [Birch trees with blue butterflies], Jake Krapowicz, undated (Folder OS Folder 8, Item 3)
  - Beach Cottage, by Jake Krapowicz, undated (Folder OS Folder 8, Item 4)
    Watercolor painting; on verso swamp scene
  - [Snow scene with barrel planter], Jake Krapowicz, undated (Folder OS Folder 8, Item 1)
    Watercolor painting - mounted on foam core
  - [Pier Scene with Gull], Jake Krapowicz, undated (Folder OS Folder 8, Item 5)
  - [Two red-sailed boats with tree], Jake Krapowicz, undated (Folder OS Folder 8, Item 2)
  - "To Stand Pipe," Karl Kravatz, undated (Folder OS Folder 5, Item 1)
  - Abstract of "Library Place", Danbury, Darr Luckenbill, undated (Item 1)
  - Cathedral Composite (St. Patrick's NYC), Harold O. Nicholson, ca. 1960 (Item 12)
    Oil on canvas, framed.
  - Middle of nowhere, Richard Procopio, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Photograph, glass frame
  - [Tree in the middle of nowhere[, Richard Procopio, undated (Item 13)
  - Cynosure, Ray Ridebock, undated (Item 2)
    Oil painting
  - [Watercolor of House on Hill], Dennis Stuart, undated (Folder OS Folder 5, Item 2)
  - Isolation Series, Are they your stars or mine?", Kim Tester, undated (Folder OS Folder 9, Item 5)
  - Barn, wheat stalks, J.M. Powell, undated (Item 15)
    Oil on canvass. Attributed upon accession to Ida Mae Wanzer. Signature on painting appears to be J.M. Powell.
  - Barn and Squantz Pond, Ida Mae Wanzer, undated (Item 14)
  - Baseball Scene, Gerald Wolfert, 1990 (Folder OS Folder 3, Item 1)
  - [Eastern or Middle Eastern man with nude women under mat], Unknown, undated (Item 7)
    Oil on paper, lacquered and pasted to masonite board. Appears to be from 1930s or 40s. May depict scene in an opium den.
  - Plaster cast, Unknown, undated (Item 8)
  - Framed WCSU Scene, Unknown, undated (Item 9)
  - Street scene with arch, Unknown, undated (Item 10)
    Print, framed.